Okay, next section, salivary gland.
Remember that the salivary glands are exocrine glands that secrete saliva.
They are divided into the major glands and the minor glands.
And remember that the major glands are three.
There is a parotid gland, a submandibular gland, and a sublingual gland.
And there are thousands of minor glands scattered throughout the oral pharyngeal mucosa.
The first disorder that we want to talk about is mumps,
and this is when you get infection with the mumps virus.
Remember that classically the mumps virus infects the parotid glands,
giving you bilateral inflamed parotid glands.
The mumps virus can also infect the testicle, giving you orchitis.
And again, remember that the feared complication of mumps
is that the patients can develop sterility.
And so orchitis would carry the risk of sterility.
Of course, that risk would only be seen in teenagers
because patients less than the age of 10 usually don't get orchitis,
whereas patients greater than the age of 10 do.
And that's why we particularly worry about orchitis occurring in a teenager
resulting in a risk of sterility.
Now, it's also possible for the mumps virus to create pancreatitis,
and that's important because remember that when you get pancreatitis,
you're going to get an elevated serum amylase,
but the serum amylase will also be elevated
due to the fact that you have salivary gland involvement.
So when you have an elevated serum amylase in a patient with mumps,
it could be due to the salivary gland because the salivary gland produces amylase,
or it could be due to the pancreatitis because in pancreatitis you also get
an elevated serum amylase.
And then the fourth place where the infection can occur is within the meninges,
and so you can get something called an aseptic meningitis,
and that can also be present in patients who have a mumps virus infection.
Psyladenitis is just inflammation of the salivary gland.
There really isn't much to say here.
What happens is that the patients develop an obstructing stone.
That's called sialolithiasis, and remember the general principle in pathology.
Anytime you block a tube, you're going to get infection behind that block.
And so when the stone obstructs, you end up getting inflammation of the salivary gland.
It's usually due to a staph aureus infection, and it's usually unilateral as well.
So that's psialatinitis.
One of the important tumors of the salivary gland to be familiar with,
and the most common tumor is a pleomorphic adenoma.
The word pleomorphic here implies that you've got multiple types of tissue.
And so this is a benign tumor composed of both stromal tissue and epithelial tissue.
It's important to note that when you've got two types of tissue, i.e. stroma and epithelium,
we often call that a biphasic tumor.
So it's a biphasic tumor.
Now the stromal component can be cartilage, for example,
and the epithelial component may have glands within it.
And so this is what we would classically see within a pleomorphic adenoma.
Now it's important to note that, again, as I've stated,
it's the most common tumor of the salivary gland, usually arises in the parotid.
And it classically presents as a mobile, painless, circumscribed mass at the region of the parotid gland.
Now this is very important because these are all of the key characteristics that we've studied concerning benign tumors.
It's mobile, meaning that it hasn't invaded local tissue.
It's painless because it hasn't invaded the facial nerve.
Now remember that the facial nerve runs right through the parotid gland.
And so when you have malignant tumors of the parotid gland,
you often have facial nerve problems, and pain may be one of them.
Also, important to note that this is a circumscribed mass,
so that the tumor is very distinct from all of the tissue surrounding it.
And all of these features are suggested that we're dealing with a benign tumor.
Now important to note, and very high yield for the purposes of examinations,
is that there's a high rate of recurrence in this tumor.
The reason why you get a high rate of recurrence in this tumor is because the tumor has irregular margins.
So if you look at this picture here, what I'm outlining here is a pleomorphic adenoma.
And what you can see is that there is some irregularity to the margins of this tumor.
So imagine if the surgeon goes in and excises this tumor,
but leaves behind a little bit of that irregularity, that can result in recurrence.
And so the reason why there is a high rate of recurrence is because surgeons will often,
or classically, an inexperienced surgeon, we should say, may not completely resect the entire tumor.
So that leads to the high rate of recurrence, as I've stated, and again, that's super high yield.
Rarely, this pleomorphic adenoma can transform into carcinoma.
And the way by which you'll make that distinction is that you'll get signs of facial nerve damage,
for example, facial nerve palsies.
And so the classic example that might show up on an examination would be a patient
who has a mass in the parotid for 10 years,
and then all of a sudden now presents with some sort of facial nerve abnormality.
So if a patient has a mass in a parotid for 10 years that isn't growing,
that suggests that you have like a pleomorphic adenoma.
And then all of a sudden, they now present with facial nerve problems.
That suggests that the tumor is now boring into the facial nerve.
And so you'd think about transformation into carcinoma.
The next tumor is called a warthens tumor.
This is a benign cystic tumor of the salivary gland.
It's the second most common salivary gland tumor.
Almost always arises in the parotid.
Now this benign cystic tumor, the classic feature is that you get abundant lymphocytes and germinal centers.
So basically, it's a cystic tumor with lymph node tissue.
That's the take-home point.
This tumor almost always arises in the parotid.
And the reason why it classically arises in the parotid is because it's not uncommon embryologically
for lymph node tissue to be associated with the parotid.
The parotid gland is one of the last glands to actually separate itself from the adjacent stroma embryologically.
And so it's often that we can see lymph node tissue within the parotid,
and that lymph node tissue can actually become a warthens tumor.
So again, it's a benign cystic tumor with lymph node tissue.
And that's why we say abundant lymphocytes and germinal centers is the classic description.
The final tumor is called a mucoepidermoid carcinoma.
And the muco means that you have mucus-producing cells or mucinous cells.
And the epidermoid means that you've got squamous cells.
So it's actually a malignant tumor that's composed of two types of epithelium,
mucinous and squamous cells.
Now, this usually arises in the parotid, and it's going to commonly involve the facial nerve.
It's a malignant tumor.
So, again, the facial nerve runs right through the parotid.
And if you have a malignant tumor of the parotid, it'll damage the facial nerve,
creating problems with the facial nerve.
And so that's important to bear in mind as well.
And that concludes our discussion of salivary gland lesions.
Salivary gland lesions.